<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Org-Mode on SqrtMinusOne</title>
    <link>https://sqrtminusone.xyz/tags/org-mode/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Org-Mode on SqrtMinusOne</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://sqrtminusone.xyz/tags/org-mode/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Extending elfeed with PDF viewer and subtitles fetcher</title>
      <link>https://sqrtminusone.xyz/posts/2022-05-09-pdf/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sqrtminusone.xyz/posts/2022-05-09-pdf/</guid>
      <description>Intro elfeed is one of the most popular Emacs packages, and it&amp;rsquo;s also one in which I ended up investing a lot of effort. I wrote about the EMMS integration and even made a custom frontpage to my liking.&#xA;However, sites frequently limit the amount of information shipped in the RSS feed. Oftentimes the entry doesn&amp;rsquo;t include the entire content (of which, by the way, this blog was guilty).&#xA;Also, there&amp;rsquo;s non-textual content, of which in this post I consider YouTube subscriptions.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A few cases of literate configuration</title>
      <link>https://sqrtminusone.xyz/posts/2022-02-12-literate/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sqrtminusone.xyz/posts/2022-02-12-literate/</guid>
      <description>A post that arose from the discussion of literate configuration on the System Crafters Discord.&#xA;I am using the literate configuration strategy (based on Emacs&amp;rsquo; Org Mode) to manage most of my configuration files. A piece of such a configuration can be as simple as an Org file, which is tangled to one or many plain-text configuration files, but it can be more.&#xA;In my opinion, a literate configuration can be more straightforward and concise than a &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo; one, thanks to Org Mode&amp;rsquo;s capabilities of working with source code.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
