<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Emacs on SqrtMinusOne</title>
    <link>https://sqrtminusone.xyz/tags/emacs/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Emacs on SqrtMinusOne</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 11 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://sqrtminusone.xyz/tags/emacs/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Declarative filesystem management with Emacs &amp; Org Mode</title>
      <link>https://sqrtminusone.xyz/posts/2023-11-11-index/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sqrtminusone.xyz/posts/2023-11-11-index/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The post describes a Johnny.Decimal-inspired filesystem structure, declared in an org file and synchronized across machines. Different folders are available on different machines.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;intro&#34;&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;My filesystem is, shall we say, not the most orderly place.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;center&gt;&#xA;&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://emacs.ch/@sqrtminusone/110514686718545191/embed&#34; class=&#34;mastodon-embed&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%; border: 0&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;script src=&#34;https://emacs.ch/embed.js&#34; async=&#34;async&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&#xA;&lt;/center&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been somewhat messy, and messy in different ways across my three machines. For instance, my laptop had work projects in &lt;code&gt;~/Code/Job&lt;/code&gt;, my work machine had just &lt;code&gt;~/Code&lt;/code&gt;, and so forth.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Strangely, I couldn&amp;rsquo;t find and existing solution to that problem. Surely, I can&amp;rsquo;t be the only one facing that issue, can I?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>916 days of Emacs</title>
      <link>https://sqrtminusone.xyz/posts/2023-04-13-emacs/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sqrtminusone.xyz/posts/2023-04-13-emacs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;style&gt;&#xA;  .quote-title {&#xA;    margin-left: 24px;&#xA;  }&#xA;&lt;/style&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Poof I made my free-time disappear&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p class=&#34;quote-title&#34;&gt;- &lt;a href=&#34;https://elken.dev&#34;&gt;Ellis Kenyő&lt;/a&gt;, on being called an &#34;elisp mage&#34;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Little did I know on the fateful day of &lt;strong&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;timestamp-wrapper&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;timestamp&#34;&gt;[2020-10-09 Fri]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, when I had installed &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gnu.org/software/emacs/&#34;&gt;GNU Emacs&lt;/a&gt;. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t thinking about the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gnu.org/philosophy/philosophy.html&#34;&gt;ethical aspects&lt;/a&gt; of free software, the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.webofstories.com/play/marvin.minsky/44&#34;&gt;aesthetics of Lisp&lt;/a&gt;, or these other things with which an occasional layperson might explain how an almost &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jwz.org/doc/emacs-timeline.html&#34;&gt;half a century old&lt;/a&gt; program can still be in &lt;a href=&#34;https://emacsconf.org/2022/talks/survey/&#34;&gt;active use&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In fact, when considering using software X for anything, the most important question to me was: can X provide a better user experience? For Emacs, the answer to most of these questions turned out to be yes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Running Gource with Emacs</title>
      <link>https://sqrtminusone.xyz/posts/2023-01-02-gource/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sqrtminusone.xyz/posts/2023-01-02-gource/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://sqrtminusone.xyz/images/gource/gource.png&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://gource.io/&#34;&gt;Gource&lt;/a&gt; is a program that draws an animated graph of users changing the repository over time.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Although it can work without extra effort (just run &lt;code&gt;gource&lt;/code&gt; in a &lt;a href=&#34;https://git-scm.com/&#34;&gt;git&lt;/a&gt; repo), there are some tweaks that can be done:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Gource supports using custom pictures for users. &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.gravatar.com/&#34;&gt;Gravatar&lt;/a&gt; is an obvious place to get these.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Occasionally, the same people have different names and/or emails in history.&lt;br /&gt;&#xA;It may happen when people use forges like &lt;a href=&#34;https://gitlab.com/&#34;&gt;GitLab&lt;/a&gt; or just have different settings on different machines. It would be nice to merge these names.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Visualizing the history of multiple repositories (e.g. frontend and backend) requires combining multiple gource logs.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;So, why not try doing that with Emacs?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Podcast transcripts with elfeed &amp; speech recognition engine</title>
      <link>https://sqrtminusone.xyz/posts/2022-09-16-vosk/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sqrtminusone.xyz/posts/2022-09-16-vosk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Edit &lt;span class=&#34;timestamp-wrapper&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;timestamp&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;2022-10-13 Thu&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; Just a couple of days after this post, OpenAI released a speech recognition model called &lt;a href=&#34;https://openai.com/blog/whisper/&#34;&gt;Whisper&lt;/a&gt;, which is so much better than anything I&amp;rsquo;ve ever seen before. I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to leave this post as it is, but check the &lt;a href=&#34;https://sqrtminusone.xyz/configs/emacs/#podcast-transcripts&#34;&gt;Emacs config&lt;/a&gt; for the updated version.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In my experience, finding something in a podcast is particularly troublesome. For example, occasionally I want to refer to some line in the podcast to make an &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/org-roam/org-roam&#34;&gt;org-roam&lt;/a&gt; node, e.g. I want to check that I got that part right.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extending elfeed with PDF viewer and subtitles fetcher</title>
      <link>https://sqrtminusone.xyz/posts/2022-05-09-pdf/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sqrtminusone.xyz/posts/2022-05-09-pdf/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;intro&#34;&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/skeeto/elfeed&#34;&gt;elfeed&lt;/a&gt; is one of the most popular Emacs packages, and it&amp;rsquo;s also one in which I ended up investing a lot of effort. I wrote about the &lt;a href=&#34;https://sqrtminusone.xyz/posts/2021-09-07-emms/&#34;&gt;EMMS integration&lt;/a&gt; and even made a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/SqrtMinusOne/elfeed-summary&#34;&gt;custom frontpage&lt;/a&gt; to my liking.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;However, sites frequently limit the amount of information shipped in the RSS feed. Oftentimes the entry doesn&amp;rsquo;t include the entire content (of which, by the way, this blog was guilty).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Also, there&amp;rsquo;s non-textual content, of which in this post I consider YouTube subscriptions. It&amp;rsquo;s possible to watch YouTube from elfeed, for instance with the aforementioned EMMS integration, but we can do more.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A few cases of literate configuration</title>
      <link>https://sqrtminusone.xyz/posts/2022-02-12-literate/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sqrtminusone.xyz/posts/2022-02-12-literate/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A post that arose from the discussion of literate configuration on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://systemcrafters.net/&#34;&gt;System Crafters&lt;/a&gt; Discord.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I am using the &lt;a href=&#34;https://leanpub.com/lit-config&#34;&gt;literate configuration&lt;/a&gt; strategy (based on &lt;a href=&#34;https://orgmode.org/&#34;&gt;Emacs&amp;rsquo; Org Mode&lt;/a&gt;) to manage most of my configuration files. A piece of such a configuration can be as simple as an Org file, which is tangled to one or many plain-text configuration files, but it can be more.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In my opinion, a literate configuration can be more straightforward and concise than a &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo; one, thanks to Org Mode&amp;rsquo;s capabilities of &lt;a href=&#34;https://orgmode.org/manual/Working-with-Source-Code.html&#34;&gt;working with source code&lt;/a&gt;. So here I present a few examples from my configuration where I think this is the case:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Using EXWM and perspective.el on multi-monitor setup</title>
      <link>https://sqrtminusone.xyz/posts/2022-01-03-exwm/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sqrtminusone.xyz/posts/2022-01-03-exwm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I wrote about &lt;a href=&#34;https://sqrtminusone.xyz/posts/2021-10-04-emacs-i3/&#34;&gt;Emacs and i3&lt;/a&gt; integration around two months ago. Shortly after however, I decided to give EXWM another try, mainly because my largest reservation - lack of performance - seems to have been resolved by updates to the native compilation since my first attempt. Or I may have lost some sensitivity to that issue. Regardless, the second dive into EXWM thus far feels successful, and I think it&amp;rsquo;s the right time to share some of my thoughts on the subject.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Getting a consistent set of keybindings between i3 and Emacs</title>
      <link>https://sqrtminusone.xyz/posts/2021-10-04-emacs-i3/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sqrtminusone.xyz/posts/2021-10-04-emacs-i3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;intro&#34;&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One advantage of EXWM for an Emacs user is that EXWM gives one set of keybindings to manage both Emacs windows and X windows. In every other WM, like my preferred &lt;a href=&#34;https://i3wm.org&#34;&gt;i3wm&lt;/a&gt;, two orthogonal keymaps seem to be necessary. But, as both programs are quite customizable, I want to see whether I can replicate at least some part of the EXWM goodness in i3.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;But why not just use EXWM? One key reason is that to my taste (and perhaps on my hardware) EXWM didn&amp;rsquo;t feel snappy enough. Also, I really like i3&amp;rsquo;s tree-based layout structure; I feel like it fits my workflow much better than anything else I tried, including the master/stack paradigm of &lt;a href=&#34;https://xmonad.org/&#34;&gt;XMonad&lt;/a&gt;​, for instance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My EMMS and elfeed setup</title>
      <link>https://sqrtminusone.xyz/posts/2021-09-07-emms/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sqrtminusone.xyz/posts/2021-09-07-emms/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;intro&#34;&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://sqrtminusone.xyz/images/emms/emms-screenshot.png&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is the current state of my quest to live in Emacs, at least in part of reading RSS and music.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Even before I lost my mind about customizing obscure keyboard-driven software, I tried Inoreader, self-hosted FreshRSS, and then newsboat from the RSS side and ncmpcpp+MPD from the audio player side. At some point, I got curious about whether I can do the same in Emacs.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The respective emacs packages, elfeed and EMMS, proved somewhat tricky to set up, i.e. I had to figure out the source code in both cases. I even submitted a small patch to EMMS to make it parse my MPD library correctly.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Replacing Jupyter Notebook with Org Mode</title>
      <link>https://sqrtminusone.xyz/posts/2021-05-01-org-python/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sqrtminusone.xyz/posts/2021-05-01-org-python/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://sqrtminusone.xyz/images/org-python/org-python-screenshot.png&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;why&#34;&gt;Why?&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://jupyter-notebook.readthedocs.io/en/stable/&#34;&gt;Jupyter Notebook&lt;/a&gt; and its successor &lt;a href=&#34;https://jupyterlab.readthedocs.io/en/stable/&#34;&gt;Jupyter Lab&lt;/a&gt; providing an interactive development environment for many programming languages are in lots of ways great pieces of software.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;But while I was using the former, and then the latter, I was also an as-full-time-as-one-can-get NeoVim user. &amp;ldquo;As one can get&amp;rdquo; is because, of course, there is no sensible way to extend the NeoVim editing experience to the Jupyter ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A possibility for change appeared with my discovery of Emacs not so long ago. Emacs, a substantially more extensible piece of software, potentially can be used for the mentioned kind of programming. So I decided to try.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiple Gmail accounts &amp; labels with Emacs</title>
      <link>https://sqrtminusone.xyz/posts/2021-02-27-gmail/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sqrtminusone.xyz/posts/2021-02-27-gmail/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;intro&#34;&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For quite some time, e-mail seemed like an anomaly in my workflow. I am a long time Gmail user, and my decade-old account has a somewhat formidable quantity of labels and filters. My messages are often assigned multiple labels, and I also like to keep only a bunch of messages in the inbox.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Although, in my opinion, Gmail web UI was and still is leagues ahead of many of its competitors and even allows keyboard-centric workflow, it&amp;rsquo;s awkward to use with a keyboard-driven browser, and for no money on Earth I would enable browser notifications.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
